hello it is March 15 2023 were in our
first discussion of chapter four in
cohort three
and there's a lot of great questions
first is there any general
comments or Reflections that anyone
wants to share about chapter four
yeah just just previously people were
reflecting on this kind of
accuracy complexity trade-off and
how much and what maths to show Ali
uh yeah as Jonathan and francoiso
mentioned uh this chapter is pretty
dense and probably one of the uh most
typical chapters in the whole book but
um in my own experience the step-by-step
tutorial paper uh is extremely helpful
uh when reading this chapter because
some of the missing gaps in the
explanations and uh some of the in my
opinion necessary details uh that are
somehow for some reason that have been
omitted from this chapter uh can be
found uh in uh quite helpful detail on
that paper so yeah I definitely highly
recommend reading that well
oh that's great I will do so the thing
is I know that the step-by-step paper is
only for discrete time but this chapter
four also good to continuous time yeah
is there a similar resource that you
could recommend for raffle Bowl matches
paper and tutorial on free energy
principle uh somehow does the same kind
of
um
not simplification but uh a kind of
pedagogical walkthrough through the
continuous time active in France so uh
both both of those papers could be seen
as complementary to each other one for
discrete and the other one for
continuous time situations
thank you out of the link here
um
any other General
comments we had chapter one introduction
then
we walked on the low road and the high
road to active inference
and now in chapter four we're at the
generative models of active inference
so
if it's an active inference generative
model it's active inference
if it's something else it's something
else
a focus in this whole textbook and field
is about how time is represented
and those who have done any kind of
dynamical systems modeling will be
familiar with a lot of like the
fundamental differences and challenges
for example continuous and discrete
representations of time and how it's
discretized time and so on
so section 4.2
from Bayesian inference to free energy
the preceding two chapters with a high
and the low road were outlining
important connections with active
inference and other paradigms
and especially the low road helped us
look at the Bayesian brain starting from
the bottom starting from the how
um
with respect to the high road
this is where we bring in
Notions of like cognitive entities
and the kinds of bounded inference or
bounded rationality that support
self-organization and persistence and
adaptive decision making
this chapter
Recaps basing inference
and specifically the variational
approach of Bayesian inference
that is what is going to connect
generative models
which are how active inference models
are specified
to the concept of free energy
which is going to be shown to be kind of
like a criteria or an imperative that's
used to fit or describe
different generative models and the data
this section is more technical than the
previous chapters appealing to a little
linear algebra
differentiation in calculus and the
Taylor series expansion
some of those topics are in the
appendices and and even the points that
people like on the the structure of what
would have been helpful to know when
those are all helpful comments to write
or to surface
there's no one single linear layout that
would have been perfect for every single
case but even just like
sharing what would have made it helpful
for any given person or what detours or
cul-de-sacs they went on
that's all really useful
those who do not want to delve into the
theoretical underpinnings May skip this
chapter
so soon
Bayes equation in 4.1
does anyone want to just bring up
anything or describe it or call it like
they see it
let's see if we have the natural
language description
so here with the active ontology we have
if you want to see like how it can be
read out
but a key issue
is that whether you're summing over
discrete opportunities
or integrating over continuous ranges
these sums are integrals
are very computationally challenging or
even intractable
the approach of variational inference
is to convert this potentially difficult
summation or integration problem
into an optimization problem
so instead of just like one Mega plug
and chug crunch the numbers and get one
outcome at the end
there's going to be a incrementally
optimizable approach
that we can iterate on
with known computational complexity
that under some or potentially a broad
range of settings
will bring us closer to the best
reasonable compromise answer
and so we've exchanged this
vast
One-Shot calculation
into something that can be incrementally
through time on a real computer
optimized
to understand how this works we need to
appeal to Jensen's inequality which says
that the log note that's not the log
squared that's a no subscript
the log of an average
is always greater than or equal to the
average of a log and figure 4.1 shows
that so does anyone
math professor or otherwise want to give
like a thought
on this figure 4.1 what is happening and
why why is this relevant
for how we're going to be continuing on
with Bayesian equations
maybe not a particularly deep thought
but um so this is because of the the
second derivative the fact that this is
um kind of curving down the the
steepness is getting less that this
holds true
um I created a little animation that I
can can link to looking at some playing
along along X
um and then comparing the the logarithm
of the um uh the expected value with the
expected value of the logarithm just to
get a bit of an intuition as to as to
why this holds true but I think that
this this image is pretty nice this sort
of shows why it is you can imagine that
any function which is curving down like
this is going to have this property and
any function which curves up is going to
have the opposite property
um I can I can paste a link into the
into the comments of the little
animation that I created there
awesome and can you maybe add one piece
how is this connected to surprise or how
does anybody see Jensen's inequality
maybe as leading to
the way that we're going to talk about
surprise
so I knew that this is going to give us
a a bound on surprise because surprise
is the average of the of X log X or P
um P of X log P of X essentially
um that we're averaging the amount of
information that we will gain on making
any particular
um uh measurement
um it's the average information that
you'll gain
um and so that's already an expectation
and it allows us to do an expectation of
X and take the logarithm of that which
gives us a bound on the on this price
thank you it's definitely like
some words that fly by and to hear it
many times is good
it does turn out that this property of
logs and there's going to be multiple
properties of logs that come in to help
us in different ways like the ability to
take two numbers that are multiplied
inside of a log and make it into log of
a plus log of B and so on but this
curvature property
is going to help us talk about expected
surprise okay I'm going to bring up the
awesome
could you connect that to any
um sampling
or or like what are we being surprised
about something on the y-axis something
on the x-axis where are the data and so
on
um so so this is just a normally
distributed X here
um so there's some probability of our X
um and then the uh what you're looking
at
um I guess in the uh in the
I've got to think about this now
um
no I don't want to say it would say
without thinking about it
um but but essentially here this is just
taking some expectation over X and
calculating the the logarithm uh of that
expectation and the expectation of the
logarithm just sampling so starting on
the left-hand side with with just one
sample and then increasing to 100
samples and just seeing how the
relationship between the the two
um uh those two pointers
cool that's that's all it's doing
cool
now we're going to take advantage of
that property so we return to equation
4.1
so this was the one with the intractable
sum or integration
we're going to return to 4.1
and multiply by an arbitrary function Q
so we took this line with Big Challenge
and we said there's some arbitrary
function Q
and anything divided by itself is one so
this is equivalent to multiplying by one
on this left side
and it turns out that Q is going to be
like this variational distribution from
a known family
with easily optimizable characteristics
that we know we can control
now
there's going to be a log taken on both
sides
so Q of X over Q of X which is
equivalent to just one
and then
there's going to be
um
the log taken on both sides
we can now interpret this expression as
an expectation fancy e not e cubed not
just a footnote again
e of a ratio between two probabilities
so
here's the P of Y of of this is the
joint probability distribution of hidden
States and data
and now this
allows us to construct joint
distribution over the one we control
natural log of that
natural log on the outside
is always greater than
the expectation of the log
of an expectation
is always greater than the expectation
of a log
log of an average
is always greater than or equal to the
average of a log
this value
so this is again this is the part that
we want to solve
and this is another way to rewrite it
that
is strictly bounded via Jensen's
inequality
to this
value
which is defined by triangle
the negative variational free energy
as a function of Q the distribution we
control and Y the data
the smaller the free energy the closer
it is to the negative log model evidence
especially because the log has these
like somewhat strange seeming properties
like it shoots off down to negative
Infinity over here and so on like and
there's negatives and positives so you
know
take it slow to see what each line is
actually telling us
um but this is the
um standard from statistical physics
what is called the negative variational
free energy
when free energy is small
it's close to the negative log model
evidence
negative log model evidence so if the
log model evidence were really high
like then the log because of it's always
going up and to the right but slowing
down in how it does that
it means you're also monotonically
getting higher model evidence
and also the natural log of P of Y is um
how that showed
any thoughts on equation 4.3
4.3 provides some intuition for the
roles of the free energy and the Q
distribution
two quantities that were difficult to
compute without the variational
approximation
so the expectation
about the distribution that we're
getting to control and parameterize
the expectation of
the likelihood
which is natural log of P
of the joint distribution between the
hidden States and the data
is
the negative variational free energy
as a functional of Q and data
Plus
an expectation of
the model likelihood of Q
there's some rearranging
bringing the F onto this side
and then using the
um properties of differences of logs
to get us to this
representation
variational free energy
with two components
the Raw
model evidence of the data
and
a KL Divergence
between the distribution we control
about X in States
and this
P distribution of x given the data
let me just add in your comment there
so Jonathan wrote um the entropy is the
average surprise
surprise is on a single measurement not
self and average it is simply the
probability of negative natural log of P
of x
thank you
the KL Divergence is defined in the
second line as the expected difference
between two different log probabilities
this is a measure sign a proper measure
of how different two probability
distributions are from one another
so
when there's no Divergence
between the distribution that is under
control
and the sort of true distribution that
we'd want to estimate
then the relative variational free
energy has been minimized because the
log model evidence is just what whatever
it is it is
with respect to being able to change Q
which is what makes the free energy
and optimizable quantity
because for a queue where you know which
knobs can be tuned
and there are methods for the
incremental optimization like on smooth
optimization Landscapes and so on then
this Divergence can be very directly
tackled
and this is just like it can be kind of
just
um
left unconsidered because it's it's a
constant with respect to the same data
assumed
what is
it can be assumed
yeah assume that whatever it is with
respect to changing the knobs on cue it
doesn't matter
because Q is not included in this term
Q only shows up here
so
um
okay yes definitely a few
um tricky
simple seeming but very ineffable
Transformations with logs
and the Bayes equation
that get us to
a form
for variational free energy
which if we remember back so long ago
is going to help us balance surprise
and there's going to be like a special
case that doesn't necessarily ever get
realized where the free energy like the
bound Divergence goes to zero
but in any situation where the
distribution p is maybe even of a
different structure than Q there's
always going to be some Divergence
however by reducing that Divergence
we will be
doing the best optimization we can um
Michael or anyone
okay yeah these are some some of the
most
pure mathy
pages in The textbook
sorry I have my mic's on it's all good
no it's it's true it's like where did
active inference go but this is totally
in it but these several pages
which maybe in a um undergraduate
statistics course could have been
unpacked into several
lectures and homeworks
are are very fundamental
but they're very much
brought in quickly here to get us to
this variational free energy
as someone who is not the mathematician
but um uh spoke it at one point and um
is grappling with this question of how
do I think about these objects in order
to speak to others about it earlier in
at the beginning there was this
um I was thinking about the original uh
uh formula as inputs to a process that
then uh there was a calculation being
done and that that input was one of the
false characterizations that um that
it's an inflow so it's not a single but
it's a it's this idea of there's a
continuous and to think of surprise as
also as a as a living flowing thing is
also one of those kind of hard to
Grapple with that we're not talking
inputs to to you know but rather flow to
float and that there's the
um the
hearing the the the variability right
what's not explained
um is is the
is is is the intuition that's hard to
cultivate for those of us who these
these these formulas just kind of
paralyzes and and it's and tried to
translate what are we learning here
um is that's where I'm I'm realizing my
existing language doesn't capture what
the mathematics is describing so I'm
contributing my my confusion I hope
articulately
thank you
um just to Jonathan's comment and then
back to that so um Jonathan yes however
you whatever format you're taking your
notes in
there's there's always going to be a way
um in the equations themselves
you could always tag anything
like you could add descriptions or just
notes or other unpackings
or other links in the equation section
or we can go and modify or revive the
math learning group
with any different notes that people
have on notation on different resources
to look at or like kind of
chapter wise descriptions of math
um
hopefully not too confused or or devalue
this too much
but I hope to bring even
um
more clarity ultimately
if you check out live stream number 52
especially the final hour of 52.2
you'll hear about Lance DeCosta sharing
about the free energy Divergence is just
one discrepancy measure that can be
utilized
in pursuit of a unified imperative for
on the inbound signal processing and on
the outbound control theory so
single processing alone is just passive
inference control theory alone
essentially has to presuppose knowledge
of the world or at least it's less
considered with it octave inference is
considering the inbound and the outbound
and
free energy
it turns out is an extremely convenient
discrepancy measure which is why even
before all of the 2000s and all of that
free energy and variational autoencoders
Bayesian statistics were already in
heavy use because free energy as abound
on surprise in Bayesian statistics is
just useful
but it's not the only discrepancy
measure but in the variational setting
where we're learning it here it is the
Divergence or the discrepancy measure
but thinking about this less as like
we're getting to active inference from
free energy what is free energy
put
the horse before the cart the cybernetic
Loop and the signal processing inbound
control theory outbound unified
imperative first
and then these are going to be different
useful approximate Bayesian calculations
but not the only calculations that can
be used
for modeling in that cybernetic setting
like just one note then Ali the KL
Divergence describes the informational
distance not exactly distance but
basically between two distributions but
he described another distance measure
the Earth movers distance how much Earth
you need to move from one distribution
to make it resemble the other
distribution since they both have an
area under the curve let's just say of
one
and those are different measures
and they have different properties there
are situations where one might be
appropriate or not so one can actually
do active inference
without free energy calculations there
could be a different discrepancy
calculation it's just that this is a
go-to choice
for the same reason why free energy
calculations are not Arcane their
workhorses in variational autoencoders
and so on Ali
it's just related to what you mentioned
uh two related piece of literature just
came to mind one is this well-known
paper A Tale of Two densities uh active
inference is inactive inference which
contrasts two interpretations of active
inference namely structural
representationalist representative
interpretation and inactive inference
representation uh which uh they
basically somehow lean towards
this is the second type of
um the interpretation and the other one
uh which is not so uh well known is a
chapter from uh this book uh called
um measuring and modeling persons and
situations by uh chapter 18 from this
book by Adam saffron
um and Colin D young uh namely
integrating cybernetic Big Five Theory
with the free energy principle uh so
this is also a really helpful synoptic
um comparative analysis between
different cybernetic and control
theories and uh active inference so yeah
I just wanted to mention those
um two papers
thank you
so again not to not to devalue this
whole variational sojourn
but this is the variational approach
that's why we went in with a queue
another approach could have been you
know this is a really intractable sum
we're going to sample from it with Monte
Carlo simulations and we're not going to
do variational distribution at all
so we can still
talk about active inference
even without this variational technique
so it's like this is not this is not the
essence of active
however variational Bayesian methods are
incredibly powerful and scalable on
Modern computers including in some
places where sampling is like going to
be costly or impossible
but it's really interesting to think
about everything technical
is a modeler's degree of freedom
once one has made the decision to have a
unified perspective on perception and
action
that is the active inference turn
and now these are modelers possibilities
sampling variational Bayesian methods
and other approximate Bayesian
computational methods
and and
[Music]
um
those paths are not always obvious
because
it's like
the variational free energy we're using
variational methods but that's not the
only method that could have been used
but then it's like
what is most commonly shown
um
so long like kind of path to return to
we got to variational free energy
as has been reached by other Bayesian
statisticians
because it's a super useful form
that takes that intractable sum or
integral
and it separates it into a constant term
which we're not going to do anything to
change
and one term where basically we have the
knob
and can completely incrementally
optimize it to reduce Divergence
because the KL Divergence
between the distribution that we control
and the one that we would want to have
no Divergence with
is literally that is the KL Divergence
is a difference of these two logs
which is also why some of those
more fundamental properties and logs
were being brought up
okay
or three to calculate free energy we
need three things data a family of
variational distributions and a
generative model
so do organisms minimize free energy
calculate free energy no
data a family of distributions and a
generative model do
again hard to sometimes
see the Rippling consequences
but this is a pure instrumentalist
expression
so cells do not minimize free energy
they don't calculate free energy
the models do
there are going to be two
families Genera of generative models
and the exact form of free energy is
going to be slightly different for these
two it's kind of like vertebrates and
invertebrates it's like there's a lot of
decisions down the line but this is like
some of the broad taxonomic divisions in
the generative models
the first is going to be dealing with
discrete State spaces and discrete
representations of time
the second is going to be dealing with
continuous variables and continuous
treatment of time
foreign
before showing what those generative
models look like figure 4.2 gives some
fun intuition
for this Bayes graph diagram format
so circles represent random variables
so those are things about which we hold
beliefs it could be a fixed or learnable
parameter or stochastic variable
and squares are probability
distributions that are like connector
pieces because they describe
relationships
and so these are laying out situations
where it's like here x is Upstream of Y
here x is Upstream causally of Y and W
here there are two causes Upstream of Y
and here is a chain
of causation
and so in this directed Bayesian graph
setting
these are sometimes called causal graphs
because they summarized the causal
influence of one variable on another
so
correlation is not causation
and then it gets a little bit
mingled because these are called
causative graphs but this could be
living in this region and this could be
having this disease
but this is just a model so that doesn't
mean living in the region is the
mechanistic cause of having the disease
and that's why we're always talking
about evaluation of different
um
possibilities
um Michael how completely do these four
representations of causality cover the
known forms of influence
um
someone can give a thought my my first
answer would be these are like this is
like subject verb subject verb object
you know subject you know these are like
the Clauses that influence Networks
are constructed from
so in the ultimate in the ultimate
um modular sense like this captures it
all a influences B
but then in the real setting with like
interacting an emergent causation
these get stitched together in complex
ways and in fact the generative models
that we're going to look at are going to
be using this kind of a visual grammar
to describe how different variables
influence each other
but it's an interesting question about
what forms of
appreciation influence and control exist
and how those are represented with base
graphs
okay A little bit of unpacking on the
um what they are talking about with uh
the disease and the diagnosis and all of
that
we get to figure four three
these are gonna be some core
visualizations
the top part of the graph is going to
show a partially observable Markov
decision process or a pomdp
and that's going to be in discrete time
in the bottom part of the graph is going
to be
displayed
and juxtaposed to highlight the
structural similarities but then there's
going to be some very very important
differences as well
and that is also going to be unpacked in
chapters 7 and 8 which are respectively
about the discrete time and the
continuous time settings
um so
these figures you will see in many
active inference papers
Thomas Parr in the recent book stream
gave a little bit of a historical
account he emphasized that earlier on
like pre 2012 there was a lot of
continuous time modeling like with eye
movement and the reflexes and motors
people then developed the discrete time
discrete octave inference
because it is classically used to model
decision making categorical and discrete
decision making
but these two kinds of models can also
be hybridized and that's called a hybrid
model so here again just to see it one
time but we'll see it again and again
it's like
it's like a rake
on the bottom and then there's action
selection part on Top
just great time continuous time
and then even the hybrid model it's like
here's the big rake
top level model and then where there's
just a little leaf
here
that has a whole
continuous time generative model grafted
on
so again like no GM
no generative model is like the active
generative model
it's like a grammar or a toolkit for
comparing and evaluating portfolios of
structurally different or parametrically
different
models
so it's not like there's one way to look
at attention there's not one way to look
at memory
there's not one map for a territory and
so on
but there's going to be just like many
kinds of
intuitive graphical operations
that this format is going to help us
talk about
like here is the past present the future
and you say well could we have like
three more can we go four time steps in
the future you could or could the
observations be smell and taste yes they
could or could could there be 10 policy
options yes there could be ten policy
options so it's like just a skeleton
that is going to be used and modified
and kind of remixed in in many many ways
um
does anyone have any like thoughts or
descriptions on figure 4.3 what's
something whether they've read on past a
section or not like what if they found
important in 4.3
and then let us like
dwell on 4.3 a little bit look to the
questions and then next week in our
second discussion we'll
continue on from here and look at more
questions
foreign
step by step
was brought up
and
this figure which I'm sure we have
pasted many times into our textbook
group coda
is working with that same graphical
grammar
of the base graph
on the left we have a prior
that is seeding a hidden State s
and then the hidden State s is emitting
an observation o
you can
set s and generate o That's generative
modeling generative AI
you can also
have o and update s that's the
recognition density so a which is called
the emission Matrix is The Tail of Two
densities
because you can have a hidden State and
generate synthetic data from it that's
generative
or you can have an observation and use
it to update your hidden State and
that's recognition so this is the Taylor
two densities in the static setting so
this is like a single image
and the image classifier label
and so generative AI is going from draw
me a cat
to generate the pixels whereas
previously there was only really
recognition AI from the pixels to oh
that's a cap
but it's static in the top left
the bottom left is going to be that same
Motif tailor two densities
but now s has a subscript for one two
and three which are three time steps
and so s is changing Through Time
the way s changes is through b which is
called a transition Matrix
so if there's like two states in uh s
you know is is it could be on the top or
the bottom
there's going to be a two by two
transition Matrix
where the diagonals are like staying
where you are and the off diagonals are
moving
and that is going to be the describing
the time evolution of the Hidden State
and then at each time
there's the Taylor two densities and the
emission of an observable
and the a matrix can be Sharp
which is like having kind of ones across
the diagonal
so you can like see the hidden State
without error or in The Other Extreme a
could just be like kind of like a wash
at which point the observation wouldn't
tell you anything about the hidden state
or in the middle is kind of like a
semi-blurry a matrix
where there's information on the hidden
state from the observation but it's not
unique for example a positive test
result doesn't mean you have
the disease
and That's a classic like Bayesian
statistic oh yes thank you a does not
have to be square Matrix
I'm using square examples but yes the
dimensionality is like a huge thing to
make sure that especially in complex
models that the dimensionality like
works out
um so this is passive dynamical
perception we're getting temperature
readings at time one two and three
and whether we have a perfect
thermometer
or whether we have like a kind of noisy
thermometer we're going to be making our
inference about the hidden State the
true temperature in the room through
time and then B describes how the
temperature in the room changes Through
Time whereas a is time independent
and it describes the mapping between
thermometer readings and temperature
this is passive inference on the left
Michael
um
again going to a different language but
in management traditionally management
has been uni-dimensional so for example
you might say we need to manage
um uh the dollars being produced in this
process or the fishery the single
species in this history and that one of
the challenges has been to look
ecosystemically instead of through a
uni-dimensional variable that is
optimized at the interplay between all
the variables and that that that's what
I'm witnessing here in a different space
and sense this kind of
multivariate management of the interplay
between all the factors
that that's my own shorthand for what
I'm what I'm thinking I'm sensing
awesome yeah the observations could be
our triple bottom line and then the
hidden State could be the unobservable
health of our organization
and so we're not just doing this like
naked optimization on an observable but
we're kind of inferring from the
observables into an unobserved space
and then that's the space that we're
describing the Dynamics on
yep now all of this has been passive
but this paper goes step by step it
introduces static perception and dynamic
perception
here's where action comes into play in
active inference
Pi is policy so there's a slight
difference between affordances which are
the actions that can be taken in a
moment like up down left right on your
joystick and policies which are
sequences of action over a given time
Horizon so with a Time Horizon of one
your affordances are your policy
repertoire
but for a Time Horizon of two is up up
down up right you know and so on so
um Pi describes policies
so that's sequences of actions that can
be taken
for the length of the time Horizon which
is a modeler's choice
so Pi describes which policies can be
taken
how are policies evaluated well in
reinforcement or reward learning you
would have utility function that
ascribes a utility value to different
policies
inactive inference we have expected free
energy
as an imperative that guides policy
selection
here free energy G
gets input from C which is our
preferences or our expectations
and so this is that fun twist with what
we expect slash prefer is like
in reward learning we would say the body
is rewarded by having a homeostatic
temperature survivable temperature bound
in this kind of preference based active
inference you say the body expects to be
in homeostasis it is surprised if it is
not
and it takes actions to reduce the
Divergence to minimize and bound its
surprisal
and so action policies are selected not
because they have a high estimated
utility
though that can be the case but rather
because the policy reduces expected free
energy
by aligning observations with
preferences
it's also important to note that policy
and action selection intervenes in the B
so this is changing how hidden States
change their time
and then this bottom version which has
not really even gone into much in the
textbook they're adding another variable
that describes like a temperature a
Precision on policy where in the
absolute zero temperature high Precision
setting
if there's two policies and one is a
little bit better you'd want the one
that's slightly better every time
in the neutral temperature if it was
5149 you'd want to select that one 51 of
the time
and the high temperature you would erase
the differences between policy choices
and you would be selecting equally
without respect to
mentioned Criterion but it's a little
bit of like a modification but also
it sets us up for some of the incredible
elaborations that we're going to see
within this visual grammar
so we're going to see hyper priors on
different variables and learning rates
and it's like this is like a circuit
board
there's no single circuit board
because you can wire things up
differently you can connect and say well
but what if there was um you know L that
that did that influence C it's like
you can make that generative model
and with Bayesian statistics you can
evaluate and juxtapose models that have
radically different anatomies
so it's like these are circuit board
designs or like Lego architectures
so there's not going to be one GM
even for a very narrow system of
Interest
any more than there would be just a
single circuit board
um
all of that and all of step by step
is in the discrete time setting
so past present and future how things
change Through Time how hidden States
emit observations
how the initial hidden state is set with
a prior
and how policy selection intervenes in
Hidden State through change that change
their time and
how preferences
shape through expected free energy
minimization policy selection
in the continuous time setting it's a
little bit different
we're gonna come to it
it turns out that there isn't explicit
prediction of past present and future
time steps but rather
generalized coordinates are used which
is to say like position velocity
acceleration and so on
generalized coordinates are used
akin to a Taylor series expansion
such that a smooth and differentiable
function is proposed
that makes continuously interpolated
predictions
without explicitly
mentioning discrete moments and giving
explicit predictions for them
so there's some pros and cons and
different settings and so on but we
return to this discrete continuous time
distinction
repeatedly
fundamentally it's a modeler's choice
often guided or constrained by the kind
of data that one has
and that's going to come up again and
again
they're laid out here in figure 4.3 to
illustrate their structural similarities
in both cases we have the kind of rake
or this like e facing down
with the hidden States changing through
time and emitting observations
caveat for you know the way that it's a
little bit different but basically
that's what's happening
and then the upstairs is the policy
selection
and that's what we see in step by step
The Rake is just static or dynamic
inference
that's signal processing
that's the common filter
and then the upstairs is policy
selection that's control theory
control theory upstairs signal
processing downstairs
all of it is being
included in the same generative model
so that we can have
summary statistics that are optimizable
for our generative model like free
energy
so that we can have a unified imperative
for perception and action
let's look to what questions we'll come
to next week
all right equation 4.10 so equation that
we haven't gotten to yet but yes there
are more
equations
including some subtleties with
subscripts and bold and so these are
definitely ones to have good readings of
and like a lot of different questions
and like why is that line doing that and
all of this
we'll come back to it
um
the expected free energy is minimized by
selecting those observations that cause
a large change in beliefs
we'll come back to it
okay a question of variational inference
and also we can use the coda latex on
Pac to make it render nicely
equation 410 same here and some more
questions on
um
equation notation so thanks for these
very careful
comments on the notation there
awesome so yeah a lot on the equations
and and it's like we can always return
to the math learning group we can set
another time
because there's
math learning questions
to help
increase the approachability of this
entire Corpus
and then there's also some really
specific technical questions
where it would be awesome to just have
like
here's what the squiggle means
and so those are like two different like
regimes of attention within the math
learning mode and the math learning mode
is just one mode that we're in overall
but but both those
um accessibility and rigor components of
math hopefully like if people are
motivated to
somehow work on that there's like a lot
of opportunity there
any final thoughts or we will return
next week
in our second discussion on four
all right great
thank you all farewell